(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I was afraid of womanhood.
لقد كنت خائفة من " الأنوثة "
Not that I'm not afraid now,
وليس أنني لست خائفة الان ..
but I've learned to pretend.
ولكن تعلمت إدعاء ذلك
I've learned to be flexible.
لقد تعلمت كيف اصبح مرنة
In fact, I've developed some interesting tools
في الحقيقة لقد طورت طرقاً مثيرة للاهتمام
to help me deal with this fear.
لتساعدني على التعامل مع هذا الخوف
Let me explain.
دعوني اشرح هذا ..
Back in the '50s and '60s, when I was growing up,
قديماً في الخمسينيات .. والستينات من القرن الماضي كنت مازلت طفلة
little girls were supposed to be kind and thoughtful
وكان يجب على الاناث الصغار ان يكن مهذبات وهادئات
and pretty and gentle and soft,
وجميلات .. وانيقات وناعمات
and we were supposed to fit into roles
وكان يتوجب علينا ان نتأقلم مع القواعد الاجتماعية
that were sort of shadowy --
والتي كانت نوعاً ما مبهمة
really not quite clear what we were supposed to be.
وكانت لا توضح لنا مالذي يجب حقاً علينا فعله
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There were plenty of role models all around us.
وكان هناك الكثير مِن مَن يمكن الاقتداء بهن
We had our mothers, our aunts, our cousins, our sisters,
كان لدينا امهاتنا .. عماتنا .. بنات عمومتنا .. إخوتنا
and of course, the ever-present media
وطبعاً الرموز التي كانت حاضرة إعلامياً
bombarding us with images and words,
التي تمطرنا بعباراتها وصورها
telling us how to be.
وتخبرنا عن الطريقة التي يجب ان نكون عليها
Now my mother was different.
ولكن والدتي كانت مختلفة ..
She was a homemaker,
لقد كانت من النوع الذي يقوم بكل شيء في المنزل
but she and I didn't go out and do girlie things together,
و لم اكن اقوم معها بأشياء أُنثوية .. ولم نكن نخرج سويةً
and she didn't buy me pink outfits.
ولم تكن تشتري لي الملابس " وردية اللون "
Instead, she knew what I needed, and she bought me a book of cartoons.
وبدلا من هذا .. كانت تشتري لي كتب الكرتون وقصص الاطفال
And I just ate it up.
وكنت أستمتع بها كثيراً .. لان هذا ما كنت أريده وكانت تعي هذا جيداً
I drew, and I drew,
كنت أرسم .. وأرسم
and since I knew that humor was acceptable in my family,
ولانني كنت أعي ان الرسم مقبول في عائلتي
I could draw, do what I wanted to do,
كان يمكنني أن أرسم كل ما أريد ان أرسمه
and not have to perform, not have to speak --
ولم اكن احتاج ان اعبر عما اريد .. لا بالاقوال و لا بالافعال
I was very shy --
كنت خجولة جداً
and I could still get approval.
وكنت احصل على ما اريد بواسطة الرسم
I was launched as a cartoonist.
وهكذا غدوت رسامة كارتون
Now when we're young,
عندما نكون صغاراً
we don't always know. We know there are rules out there,
نحن لا نعي دوما .. بل نحن نعي ان هناك قواعد ..
but we don't always know --
ولكننا لا نعي مكنونها دوماً
we don't perform them right,
ولا نطبقها بصورة صحيحة دوماً
even though we are imprinted at birth
حتى لو كانت تلك القواعد تسري علينا
with these things,
منذ ولادتنا
and we're told
فيتم تلقينُنا ..
what the most important color in the world is.
اللون الافضل في العالم
We're told what shape we're supposed to be in.
الشكل الذي يجب ان نبدو عليه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We're told what to wear --
ومالذي يتوجب علينا إرتداءه
-- and how to do our hair --
وكيف نشذب شعرنا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- and how to behave.
وكيف نتصرف
Now the rules that I'm talking about
إن القواعد التي أتحدث عنا
are constantly being monitored by the culture.
يتم مراقبتها على الدوام من قبل " ثقافة المجتمع "
We're being corrected,
ويتم تصحيحنا على الفور
and the primary policemen are women,
والمراقب الاساسي هنا هن " النسوة "
because we are the carriers of the tradition.
لأننا " حُماة " التقاليد واللاتي يحملنَّ رسالتها
We pass it down from generation to generation.
فنحن ننقلها من جيل الى جيل
Not only that --
وليس فحسب
we always have this vague notion
اننا دوماً نملك هذا المفهوم الغامض ..
that something's expected of us.
الذي نعتقد ان هناك شيء ما " متوقع " منا للقيام به ..
And on top of all off these rules,
لا بل فوق كل هذه القواعد ..
they keep changing.
انها تتغير على الدوام " القوانين الثقافية "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We don't know what's going on half the time,
ونحن لا نعرف مالذي يحدث .. في معظم الوقت
so it puts us in a very tenuous position.
وهذا يضعنا في موقف ضعف
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now if you don't like these rules,
وإن لم تعجبك هذه القواعد ..
and many of us don't --
والكثير منا لا تعجبهنَّ تلك القواعد ..
I know I didn't, and I still don't,
فأنا لا تعجبني .. وما تزال لا تعجبني !
even though I follow them half the time,
رغم أنني أتبعها معظم الوقت
not quite aware that I'm following them --
دون أن أدري أنني أتبعها من الاساس !
what better way than to change them [than] with humor?
وأي طريقة أفضل لتغير هذه القواعد .. من الرسوم الكرتونية؟
Humor relies on the traditions of a society.
ان المزاح يعتمد في الاساس على عادات المجتمع
It takes what we know, and it twists it.
انه يعتمد على ما نعرفه.. ومن ثم تدور حوله ..
It takes the codes of behavior and the codes of dress,
انها تعبر عن شفرات السلوك و قواعد التصرف .. والملبس ..
and it makes it unexpected,
وهي تخرج بصورة غير متوقعه .. وكأن هذه القواعد غريبة جداً
and that's what elicits a laugh.
وهذا ما يولد الضحك
Now what if you put together women and humor?
والآن ماذا لو جمعت النسوة والرسوم الكارتونية ؟
I think you can get change.
أعتقد اننا سنحصل على تغير
Because women are on the ground floor,
لان النساء هن أساس هذه الافكار ..
and we know the traditions so well,
ونحن نعي التقاليد جيداً
we can bring a different voice to the table.
وهذا سيجلب رأياً جديداً الى الساحة .
Now I started drawing
لقد بدأت ارسم
in the middle of a lot of chaos.
في وسط الكثير من الفوضى
I grew up not far from here in Washington D.C.
لقد نشأت في مكان قريب من واشنطن العاصمة
during the Civil Rights movement, the assassinations,
أثناء حركة الحقوق المدنية .. والاغتيالات
the Watergate hearings and then the feminist movement,
وجلسات استماع فضيحة ووتر جيت .. وظهور الحركات النسوية
and I think I was drawing,
واعتقد انني كنت أرسم
trying to figure out what was going on.
محاولة أن استوعب مالذي كان يحصل حينها
And then also my family was in chaos,
وكما المجتمع كانت عائلتي كذلك ..في فوضى
and I drew to try to bring my family together --
وكنت أرسم محاولة ان اجمع عائلتي ..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- try to bring my family together with laughter.
محاولة ان اجمع عائلتي سويةً عن طريق الضحك
It didn't work.
ولكن لم ينجح ذلك
My parents got divorced, and my sister was arrested.
لقد تطلق والدي .. وتم اعتقالي مع أُختي ..
But I found my place.
ولكني وجدت مكاني الذي كنت أبحث عنه
I found that I didn't have to wear high heels,
مكان لا يتوجب علي فيه ان ارتدي كعباً عالياً
I didn't have to wear pink,
ولا يتوجب علي ان ارتدي الالوان الزهرية
and I could feel like I fit in.
مكانٌ اشعر انني انتمي إليه
Now when I was a little older, in my 20s,
عندما كنت في العشرينيات من عمري
I realized there are not many women in cartooning.
انتبهت .. انه لا يوجد الكثير من راسمات الكاركاتير
And I thought, "Well, maybe I can break
وقلت انه ربما يمكنني ان احطم هذه الهالة " الذكورية "
the little glass ceiling of cartooning,"
هو رسم الكارتون والكاركاتير
and so I did. I became a cartoonist.
وهكذا فعلت ..فقد غدوت راسمة كاركاتير
And then I thought -- in my 40s I started thinking,
ومن ثم فكرت .. في الاربعينيات من عمري بدأت افكر ..
"Well, why don't I do something?
حسناً .. لماذا لا اقوم بشيء مفيد ..
I always loved political cartoons,
لطالما أحببت الرسوم الكارتونية السياسية
so why don't I do something with the content of my cartoons
فقلت لماذا لااستخدم الكاركاتير في هذا النسق
to make people think about the stupid rules that we're following
لكي اجعل الناس تفكر بمدى غباء القواعد التي يتبعونها
as well as laugh?"
واجعلهم يضحكون منها أيضاً ؟
Now my perspective
حسناً .. إن منظوري
is a particularly --
هو في الحقيقة ..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- my perspective is a particularly American perspective.
ان منظوري .. هو في الحقيقة منظور أمريكي ..
I can't help it. I live here.
لا يمكنني أن انكر هذا .. فأنا أعيش هنا ..
Even though I've traveled a lot,
رغم أنني اسافر كثيراً
I still think like an American woman.
فأنا ما زلت أفكر كإمرأة أمريكية
But I believe that the rules that I'm talking about
ولكنني مقتنعة أن القواعد التي أتحدث عنها
are universal, of course --
هي قواعد عالمية ..
that each culture has its different codes of behavior
صحيح ان لكل ثقافة نوعٌ خاص بها من التقاليد والعادات
and dress and traditions,
والملابس والثقافات ..
and each woman has to deal with these same things
ولكن كل النساء في انحاء العالم .. يتوجب عليها أن تتعامل مع هذه القواعد
that we do here in the U.S.
بنفس الطريقة التي تتعامل معها النسوة في الولايات المتحدة الامريكية مع القواعد
Consequently, we have.
بصورة دائمة .. نحن ..
Women, because we're on the ground, we know the tradition.
.. النساء ... لاننا الاساس . .ولاننا نعي التقاليد
We have amazing antennae.
فنحن نملك " وسائل استشعار رائعة "
Now my work lately
ان رسمي مؤخراً ..
has been to collaborate with international cartoonists,
جعلني أتعاون مع الرسامين الكاركاتورين العالميين
which I so enjoy,
وهذا شيء انا فرحةٌ به
and it's given me a greater appreciation
ولقد جعلني هذا أقدر بشدة
for the power of cartoons
قدرة الرسوم الكارتونية
to get at the truth,
على قول الحقيقة
to get at the issues quickly and succinctly.
بصورة سريعة وموجة
And not only that, it can get to the viewer
وهي أيضاً تستطيع ان تصل الى المشاهد
through not only the intellect, but through the heart.
لا عن طريق الفكر فحسب .. بل عن طريق القلب أيضاً
My work also has allowed me to collaborate
وعملي أيضاً سمح لي بأن اتعاون مع
with women cartoonists from across the world --
الراسمات الكارتونية حول العالم
countries such as Saudi Arabia,
من دول مثل المملكة العربية السعودية
Iran, Turkey,
إيران . .تركيا
Argentina, France --
الارجنتين .. فرنسا
and we have sat together and laughed
وقد اجتمعت معم .. وضحكنا سوية
and talked and shared our difficulties.
وتحدثنا وتشاركنا فيما يخص اختلافاتنا
And these women are working so hard to get their voices heard
وهذه النسوة تعمل بجهد كبير لكي تعبر عن نفسها ..
in some very difficult circumstances.
في ظروف شديدة الصعوبة
But I feel blessed to be able to work with them.
وانا اشعر بالامتنان لكوني أعمل معهم
And we talk about
ونحن نتحدث
how women have such strong perceptions,
عن كيف ان النساء تملك تصورات قوية ..
because of our tenuous position
بسبب الموقع الحرج الذي هنَّ فيه
and our role as tradition-keepers,
وبسبب وظيفتنا كحاميات للثقافة
that we can have the great potential
فاننا نملك القدرة الكبيرة
to be change-agents.
على أن نغدو " محركات تغيير "
And I think, I truly believe,
وانا اعتقد .. بل أُؤمن
that we can change this thing
بأننا يمكننا أن نغير هذه " القيود الثقافية "
one laugh at a time.
بضحكة واحدة تلو الأُخرى
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)